<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-2"?>
<page menu="install">
	<sec tit="Common part">
		<p>
			First you need to install MTA (at this time only qmail is supported).
			I created patch for qmail including most needed stuff like
			smtp-auth, ssl, etc., more informations are located at 
			<a href="http://new.foo-baz.com/proj/q-p/">http://new.foo-baz.com/proj/q-p/</a>.
		</p>

		<p>
			Following installation procedure was created using OpenBSD 3.4 box, but
			it will work also for Linux. Commands are executed as root:
		</p>
	
		<ol>
			<li>groupadd vq</li>
			<li>useradd -g vq -d /var/vq vq</li>
			<li>bunzip2 -c vq-*.tar.bz2 | tar -xf -</li>
			<li>cd vq</li>
			<li>
				vim *.lib *.inc<br/>
				Files *.inc includes options for compiler telling where to look
				for include files. Files *.lib point to libraries and directories.
				On OpenBSD usually you need add -liconv to iconv.lib, Linux's
				glibc includes iconv (so you need to remove this line).
				Default options may not work for you (it's not an error), you
				must set values depending on your system configuration.
				Sometimes you will need to add some other libraries, I found
				that sablotron on OpenBSD 3.4 references functions from readline, 
				ncurses.
			</li>
			<li>
				vim comp-so compile make-so make-lib<br/>
				Comp* are used to call compiler so you may put there
				optimization options. Check files if they match your system.
				If you compile vq on system not listed in 
				<a href="ports.html">Documentation::Supported Systems</a> please
				send me an information.
			</li>
			<li>
				vim conf/*<br/>
				Edit you configuration files.
			</li>
			<li>
				make<br/>
				This starts compilation. I'm using gcc 2.95.5 and 3.2.2.
				If you encounter any problems please give me feedback.
				I'll try to fix them ASAP. Also if you want to port this
				package on other systems I will help.
			</li>
			<li>
				./install<br/>
				Installing files in home.
			</li>
			<li>
				Add home/lib to linker's seach path. On OpenBSD you need
				to edit /etc/rc.conf, variable shlib_dirs (this works
				after restart, to update current database run 
				ldconfig -m home/lib). On Linux add path to /etc/ld.so.conf and
				run ldconfig.
			</li>
			<li>
				Depending on system you should set SUID/SGID and owners
				for all home/bin/qmail* files. They must have an access
				to qmail/control, qmail/users, and qmail's processes (qmail-send).
			</li>
			<li>
				That should be all. You have now working vq system.
			</li>
		</ol>
	</sec>

	<sec tit="Using PostgreSQL as a database server">
		<ol>
			<li>
				Install <a href="http://www.postgresql.org">PostgreSQL</a>.<br/>
				I try to keep using the most current stable version.
				I don't support older versions. Install also libpqxx, use
				newest stable version.
			</li>
			<li>
				Create user, default is &quot;mail&quot;.
			</li>
			<li>
				Create database, default is &quot;mail&quot;. It's adviced
				to set encoding to UTF-8 (programs in contrib relay on this
				setting).
			</li>
			<li>
				Go to the doc/pgsql directory. There's list of things
				you need to do. It also contains SQL files that are
				used to create basic database structure.
			</li>
		</ol>
	</sec>

	<sec tit="Programs in contrib">
		<p>
			I think that after installing vq you'll be able to install the
			rest of programs. There may be problems with hosting and
			freemail modules. They require to add some specific tables to database.
			Run some daemons. I assume that senior administrators will
			handle this. If you are interested in developing/using them
			on your site you can contact me, I'll try to help.
		</p>
	</sec>
</page>
