<chapter id="arch">
	<title>Architecture</title>

	<para>
		This chapter describes different parts of v-q system.
	</para>

	<section id="arch.parts">
		<title>Main parts</title>

		<para>
			V-q is a modularized system. Each of subsystems is a separate
			interface accessed via CORBA protocol. This means that you
			can replace any part at any time. It's matter of configuration.
		</para>

		<figure>
			<title>Architecture in a picture</title>
			<graphic fileref="../imgs/" format="PNG"/>
		</figure>
	</section>

	<section id="arch.ivq">
		<title>Interface ivq</title>

		<para>
			This is the most important interface. It is used directly
			by client programs. It is the core of the system. This module
			is responsible for integration with a mail transfer agent.
			Usually this module creates and maintains data structures on
			disk, MTA's configurations, etc.
		</para>

		<para>
			This module calls methods from <link linkend="arch.iauth">iauth</link>
			interface.
		</para>

		<section id="arch.ivq.cqmailvq">
			<title>cqmailvq</title>
			
			<para>
				At this time there's only one implementation of 
				<link linkend="arch.ivq">ivq</link> represented
				by cqmailvq class, and by qmailvqd daemon.
			</para>

			<para>
				This object integrates with 
				<ulink url="http://www.qmail.org">qmail</ulink> MTA. It
				handles updating qmail's configuration, managing
				users' maildirs, directories hierarchy, etc.
			</para>

			<para>
				For some actions it uses small, helper programs
				that are responsible for qmail's configuration updates.
				This way priviledges can be separated - qmail's configuration
				can be owned by a user other than the user which runs
				qmailvqd.
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section id="arch.iauth">
		<title>Interface iauth</title>

		<para>
			This interface represents authorization backend which
			is responsible for storing informations about existing
			domains and users.
		</para>

		<para>
			Usually this interface implementations does not create
			any entries in filesystem. They operate only on a specified
			database.
		</para>

		<para>
			This interface is used by <link linkend="arch.ivq">ivq
			implementations</link>. You should not use it directly.
			If you think that some feature should be added
			to ivq please contact developers.
		</para>

		<section id="arch.iauth.cpgsqlauth">
			<title>cpgsqlauth</title>

			<para>
				This implementation of <link linkend="arch.iauth">iauth
				interface</link> operates on a PostgreSQL database.
			</para>

			<para>
				It stores all informations in a database. Doesn't create
				or use any files other than configuration.
			</para>

			<para>
				It is represented by pgsqlauthd daemon.
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>
</chapter>
