<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<page menu="intro">
	<p>
		Project goal is to create virtual domains managing system, it should
		be easy to setup, create and maintain. It should be also very reliable and
		fast - it's designed for big sites. It does not support real users and
		it won't. 
	</p>

	<p>
		What vq won't do at any time in the future: 
		<ul>
			<li>support POP3 authorization based relaying as vpopmail does - use SMTP-AUTH!</li>
			<li>support real users</li>
			<li>support any other mailboxes type than Maildir</li>
		</ul>
	</p>

	<p>
		Current futures:
		<ul>
			<li>PostgreSQL based authorization</li>
			<li>PostgreSQL based logging of user's authorizations</li>
		</ul>
	</p>

	<p>
		If you think that some future is missing you're welcome to add it or
		if you can't but think it should be implemented you can contact author.
	</p>

	<p>
		Following is a list of programs in contrib directory:
	</p>
	
	<sec tit="freemail">
		This module will support options associated with free e-mail accounts.
		At this time it include only option to change informations about
		user (sex, country, city, education level, etc.).
	</sec>

	<sec tit="hosting">
		This module will support options associated with hosting servers.
		At this time it supports: adding new e-mail accounts to domain,
		setting FTP access, removing users, access to WWW usage logs.
		Setting aliases for WWW.
	</sec>

	<sec tit="vqsignup">
		Simple program that allows users to create new e-mail accounts.
	</sec>

	<sec tit="vquserrm">
		Removes user.
	</sec>

	<sec tit="host_add">
		Adds domain.
	</sec>

	<sec tit="pg2fs">
		Used with hosting module. It's used to configure tinydns, dnscache.
		Hosting module after changing data calls stored in SQL server 
		functions from <a href="http://iidea.pl/~paweln/proj/pgutil">pgutil 
		package</a>. They create simple files which are processed by pg2fs
		to create tinydns and dnscache configuration.
	</sec>

	<sec tit="valid">
		Small library. Includes functions used to validate informations as
		data, polish tax number, polish post code, etc.
	</sec>

	<sec tit="vqsignup1">
		Special version of vqsignup which collects information about user
		(sex, education level, city, country). It's used to create free
		e-mail service.
	</sec>

	<sec tit="vqwww">
		Account manager. Includes modules that allows to: change password,
		set e-mail redirection, set automatic response, see history of login.
		It support dynamic loading of shared libraries, so it may be easily
		extended.
	</sec>
</page>
